Guide to the Hal and Barbara Dodge Borland Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hal and Barbara Borland papers
1904-1990
YCAL MSS 570
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
43.8
(60 boxes) + 1 portfolio
The Hal and Barbara Dodge Borland Papers contain writings, correspondence, printed material, and personal papers documenting the journalism and literary career of Hal Borland, and the literary career of his wife, Barbara Dodge Borland, spanning the years 1904 to 1990.
43.8 linear feet (60 boxes, 1 portfolio)
Borland, Hal, 1900-1978
Borland, Barbara Dodge
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hal and Barbara Dodge Borland, 1965-1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 52, 59-60: Restricted Fragile Material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Hal Borland (1900-1978)
Harold Glen Borland, American author, journalist, and naturalist, was born in Sterling, Nebraska to William Arthur and Sarah Clinaburg Borland on May 14, 1900. Borland grew up in Flagler, Colorado, where his parents owned and edited a weekly newspaper. From 1918 to 1920 Borland attended the University of Colorado where he studied engineering while also working for Denver Post and Flagler News. Realizing that his true avocation was as an author, Borland moved to New York where he attended Columbia University's School of Journalism, obtaining a Bachelor in Literature in 1923. Borland also worked as a reporter for the Brooklyn Times, United Press, and King Features Service at this time.
After graduation Borland spent several years traveling across the United States working for various newspapers, including stints in Salt Lake City (Utah), Carson City (Nevada), Fresno and San Diego (California), and Marshall (Texas), before returning to Colorado in 1925 to work for Stratton Press.
While living in New York Borland met his first wife, Helen Alice Le Bene (circa 1900-1944), who was also a graduate of the Columbia School of Journalism (1923). Hal and Helen Borland had three sons: Harold Glen, Junior, Donal W., and Neil F. Borland. Helen Borland also pursued a career as a journalist, publishing articles and book reviews in magazines. She died at the age of forty-four in 1944.
In 1926 Borland moved to Philadelphia, where he would live until 1937, working for Curtis Newspapers, Philadelphia Morning Sun, and Philadelphia Morning Ledger.
In 1937 Borland began writing for the New York Times, first as a staff writer for the New York Times Sunday Magazine (1937-1943) and then in 1942 as an editorial writer for the New York Sunday Times, a position he would hold until his death in 1978.
Parallel to his career as a journalist, Borland wrote short stories, novels (including westerns under the pseudonym Ward West), biographical novels, non-fiction, and a play. Borland began writing poetry and novels while still a student, with his publications including Heaps of Gold (1922), a collection of verse, and Rocky Mountain Tipi Tails (1924), a young adult novel.
However, Borland is perhaps best known for his nature writing. He was involved in a number of conservation efforts and his editorials for the New York Times, and later for the Berkshire Eagle (1958-1978), Pittsburgh Press (1966-1978), and Torrington Register (1971-1978), focused largely on the natural world and his experience as an outdoorsman. Borland's nature writing for the New York Times was compiled in Sundial of the Seasons: A Selection of Outdoor Editorials from the New York Times (1964) and Twelve Moons of the Year (1979). In addition to his journalism, Borland's nature writings also include An American Year: Country Life and Landscapes Through the Seasons (1946), Beyond Your Doorstep: A Handbook to the Country (1962), Countryman: A Summary of Belief (1965), Hill Country Harvest (1967), and Homeland: A Report from the Country (1969), among others. For his writing on the outdoors he won the Meeman Award for Conservation Writing (1966), John Burroughs Medal for Distinguished Nature Writing (1968), and the Interpretive Naturalists Award (1973).
On August 10, 1945 Borland married Barbara Ross Dodge, who was also an author and had studied at the Columbia School of Journalism. In 1952 they moved to Salisbury, Connecticut. Hal and Barbara Borland collaborated on a number of writing projects together, including stories for Collier's and Good Housekeeping.
Borland died of emphysema on February 22, 1978 in Sharon, Connecticut.
Barbara Dodge Borland (1904-1991)
Barbara Ross Dodge was born to Harry George and Grace Cross Dodge in Waterbury, Connecticut, in 1904. Dodge attended Crosby High School and Saint Margaret's School, where she excelled at poetry. She continued her education at Oberlin College (1922-1923) and then Columbia University's School of Journalism (1923), but left both institutions before receiving a degree in order to pursue a writing career. Dodge served as an editor for a number of publications before running the New York City Writers Workshop from 1934 to 1938. Dodge had one daughter, Diana Butler Thomson (1935-2000). In 1945 Dodge married Hal Borland, with whom she collaborated on a number of short stories and articles, which were published in Colliers, McCalls, Good Housekeeping, Cosmopolitan, and others (1946-1956). In 1962 Dodge published The Greater Hunger. Dodge wrote a column about gardening for the Berkshire Eagle and published This is the Way My Garden Grows: And Comes into My Kitchen in 1986. Following Borland's death, Dodge edited and published Hal Borland's Twelve Moons of the Year (1979).
Scope and Contents
The collection contain writings, correspondence, printed material, and personal papers documenting the journalism and literary career of Hal Borland, and the literary career of his wife, Barbara Dodge Borland, spanning the years 1904 to 1990.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. 1965 and 1981 Acquisitions, 1921-1981. II. April 1991 Acquisition, 1904-1990.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, correspondence and writings can be found in all two groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Borland, Barbara Dodge; Borland, Hal, 1900-1978
- I. 1965 and 1981 Acquisitions, 1921-1981; 36.42; (44 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  This group contains writings, correspondence, research files, printed material, and personal papers of Hal and Barbara Borland, from 1921 to 1981.
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 319
  - Notes and note cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Book of Days, proofs, circa 1976; 2 (Box 1)
  - Book of Days, typescript carbon, circa 1976 (Box 1)
  - Book of Days, typescript carbon and newspaper clippings, circa 1976 (Box 1)
  - Book of Days, typescripts, corrected, circa 1976; 3 (Box 1)
  - "Borland family novel," typescript notes, undated (Box 2)
  - University of Colorado, correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Columbia School of Journalism, correspondence, 1960-1968 (Box 2)
  - Lakeville Journal, correspondence and contributions, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - "Buckley," subject file on McCarthyism, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Adirondack Life, correspondence and contributions, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - American Heritage Company, correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Harper Dictionary of Contemporary Usage (William Morris), correspondence and contributions, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
  - When the Legends Die, chronology and clippings, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - When the Legends Die, movie materials, undated (Box 2)
  - Thoreau speeches, correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Speeches and notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Sundial of the Seasons, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Countryman, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1965 (Box 2)
  - King of Squaw Mountain, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Penny, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Penny, correspondence, reviews, and promotional material, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Homeland, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Harper & Brothers, correspondence, 1957-1967 (Box 2)
  - Saturday Review, correspondence and contributions, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Berkshire Farm for Boys, correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - Country Editor's Boy, promotional material and reviews, circa 1970 (Box 2)
  - Country Editor's Boy, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Sundial of the Seasons, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Our Natural World, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Our Natural World, reviews, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - Environment, research material, undated (Box 2)
  - When the Legends Die, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Vermont Life Magazine, correspondence and contributions, 1967 (Box 2)
  - American Heritage Publishing Co., correspondence, 1969 (Box 2)
  - University of Colorado, correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Lillard, Richard G. "Books in the Field: Nature and Conservation," Wilson Library Bulletin, 1969 October (Box 2)
  - English for American Indians, 1971 (Box 2)
  - John Burroughs Memorial Association, correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Chestnuts," draft, correspondence and printed material, 1962-1975 (Box 3)
  - This Week Magazine, correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 3)
  - This World of Wonder, scrapbook of reviews and comments, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Enduring Pattern, scrapbook of reviews and comments, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Arno Press, correspondence, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Bartholomew's Cobble Field Day, correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Countryman, reviews, 1963-1973 (Box 3)
  - Conservation and ecology, subject file, 1963-1973; 2 (Box 3)
  - Progressive Magazine, issues and tear sheets, 1964-1978; 3 (Box 3)
  - Audubon Magazine, article draft and correspondence, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Book reviews and comments, 1964-1977 (Box 3)
  - Unsorted correspondence and writings, 1960-1977; 2 (Box 3)
  - Reviews and tributes, clippings, 1958-1977 (Box 3)
  - This World of Wonder, rejection letters, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Beatty, C. Francis, correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 3)
  - When the Legends Die, correspondence with Martin Secker & Warburg Ltd., 1963 (Box 3)
  - Milne, Lorus and Margery, correspondence, 1958-1968 (Box 3)
  - Articles, printed versions (clippings and tear sheets), 1940-1977 (Box 3)
  - Book reviews, clippings and typescript, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - A Place to Begin, reviews, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Little Cumberland Island Association, correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - "Notes and Memoranda," binder, undated (Box 3)
  - The Golden Circle, drafts and correspondence, 1977, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry, typescripts, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - "Stories, ideas, and work papers," typescripts, undated (Box 4)
  - Weygant, Noemi (sister), correspondence, 1959-1975; 2 (Box 4)
  - Borland Country, reviews, 1972 (Box 4)
  - New York World's Fair clippings, 1939-1940
  - Book of Days, reviews, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Hill Country Harvest, scrapbook of reviews and comments, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Hill Country Harvest, reviews, 1967-1973 (Box 4)
  - When the Legends Die, scrapbook of movie reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Bartholomew's Cobble, correspondence and articles, 1970-1975 (Box 4)
  - "In Beauty May They Walk," Acorn, correspondence, draft, and printed version, 1971 (Box 4)
  - "Thanksgiving," drafts and correspondence, 1943-1949 (Box 4)
  - "Man, Most Mysterious Animal," drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - Unsorted correspondence, writings, and printed material, undated (Box 4)
  - Unsorted typescript drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - Book reviews, 1954-1972 (Box 4)
  - "America, Here She Stands," draft, undated (Box 4)
  - Research material, undated (Box 4)
  - "Eagle Columns - Ideas," typescripts, undated (Box 4)
  - Book of Days, correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 4)
  - A Place to Begin: the New England Experience, correspondence with Sierra Club Books, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Our Natural World, correspondence with Doubleday, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
  - Progressive Magazine, issues, tear sheets and drafts of articles, 1973-1979, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Johnson, Bessie, correspondence, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
  - "Clips and tear-sheets, H.B. Articles, etc. 1965," scrapbook (Box 5)
  - When the Legends Die, correspondence with Wellpinit High School students, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Seasons, typescript captions and correspondence, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Unsorted clippings and tear sheets, undated (Box 5)
  - "Cowboys of the World," notes, undated (Box 5)
  - "Silent Night," drafts, 1950 (Box 5)
  - The Golden Circle, reviews, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 5)
  - This Hill This Valley, excerpt, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with students, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - "Wanted: Ethics, Not Codes," drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - "Indian Tales," notes and drafts, undated (Box 5)
  - Reader's Digest, correspondence and drafts of articles, 1949-1968; 2 (Box 5)
  - American Dream, notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Canaan Airport Controversy, clippings, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Selections of H.B. writings read at the dedication of Hal Borland Trail, typescript, 1978 (Box 5)
  - "The Appointment," draft, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Unsorted writings, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Musumi, Satoko, correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Untitled article for Columbia School of Journalism, typescript, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Professional correspondence, 1946-1977 (Box 5)
  - Progressive Magazine, correspondence, 1964-1977; 2 (Box 5)
  - Lippincott, correspondence, 1968-1975; 7 (Box 6)
  - Indiana University Press, correspondence, 1974 (Box 6)
  - "Great Bearington Speech," typescript and correspondence, 1956 (Box 6)
  - McGraw Hill, correspondence, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Research material, clippings and notes, 1945-1947 (Box 6)
  - "The Man Next Door," typescript drafts, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Corinth Machinery Co., articles and notes, 1938-1949 (Box 6)
  - "Florida: Dream and Reality," typescript carbon draft, correspondence, and clippings, 1951 (Box 6)
  - "Sam Jordan: Shrimper," typescript drafts and correspondence, 1949 (Box 6)
  - "The Price of Yesterday," typescript draft, undated (Box 6)
  - "Lovelorn," typescript drafts, 1952 June 21 (Box 6)
  - "By Proxy," typescript draft, 1948 April 28 (Box 6)
  - "Uncle Oscar's Memory," typescript draft, 1948 June 11 (Box 6)
  - "Girl Cabin," typescript draft and correspondence, 1952 (Box 6)
  - "So With the Heart," typescripts, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Lambs," typescript drafts, 1951 April 10 (Box 6)
  - "Mother Will Love You," typescript outline, 1949 November 15 (Box 6)
  - "Bittersweet," typescript draft, 1950 January 11 (Box 6)
  - "Posey and the Strand of Truth," typescript draft, 1950 April 2 (Box 6)
  - "Bare Knuckle Diplomacy," typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - "Yon Rising Moon," typescript, 1948 February 15 (Box 6)
  - Holiday Magazine, research material, undated (Box 6)
  - "The Old Lady," typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - "How to Write and Sell Non-Fiction," typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - "One Man's Way," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Grandmother," typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Popular Science, research material, 1942 (Box 7)
  - "Water for Thirsty Land," Sunday New York Times article, drafts, correspondence, and research material, 1951 (Box 7)
  - "The Man Who Played God," drafts, 1952 October 23 (Box 7)
  - "Beginning of Career," typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Renaissance," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "How to Shoot a Buffalo," typescript carbon and correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 7)
  - "The Berry Patch," typescript carbon and correspondence, 1948-1954 (Box 7)
  - "Memo from Dr. Case," typescript carbon, 1948 October 29 (Box 7)
  - "Heartblood," "Slugger," and "Hero," typescript carbons, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Hounds that Bark," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Winter's Deceptive Sleep," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Failure," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Indian Was a Hunter," typescript carbon and correspondence, 1949 (Box 7)
  - "The Dairyman's Dilemma," typescript carbon and correspondence, 1954 (Box 7)
  - "Discipline," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Local Postoffice, U.S.A.," typescript carbon, correspondence, notes and clippings, 1954 (Box 7)
  - "Showdown," typescript carbon, 1949 July 26 (Box 7)
  - "Delilah" and "Heeled," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Comeback," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Serpent in the Garden," typescript and typescript carbon, 1950 January 31 (Box 7)
  - "I Won't Bore You with the Details," typescript and typescript carbon, 1935 April 1 (Box 7)
  - "The Man with a Dream," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Bug in a Bottle," typescript carbon, 1949 January 12 (Box 7)
  - Better Homes & Gardens, correspondence, articles, and research material, 1946-1950 (Box 7)
  - Hell's Full of High Silk Hats, typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Second Chance," typescript carbon, 1951 April 30 (Box 7)
  - "Freeze-Up," typescript carbon, 1948 (Box 7)
  - "Catbird in the Apple Tree," typescript carbon, 1946 October (Box 7)
  - "Molly, My Darlin," typescript carbon, 1954 March 20 (Box 7)
  - "Autumn," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "God's Vigilante," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "Angeline," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Cry in the Night," typescript carbon, 1950 January 15 (Box 7)
  - "Orchids," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - How to Write & Sell Non-Fiction, typescript carbon, undated (Box 7)
  - "An American Year," typescript carbon, 1943-1945 (Box 7)
  - Wapiti Pete, typescript carbon, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 8)
  - "Discipline," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - Homeland, reviews, 1969 (Box 8)
  - "Homecoming," typescript carbon, 1953 October 15 (Box 8)
  - "Rolling Down to Rio," typescript carbon, 1958 November 3 (Box 8)
  - "Price-Tag," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "A Countryman's Report," typescript carbon, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Research file, printed material, undated (Box 8)
  - "A Master of Policy," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Blairs Die Young," typescript, undated (Box 8)
  - "Hometown Makes Good," typescript carbon and research material, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Mark of the Hoof," typescript carbon, 1949 July 17 (Box 8)
  - "Banners Flying," typescript carbon, 1948 July 11 (Box 8)
  - "Without Hokum" and "Hollywood Love Story," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "Henry and the Little Birds," typescript, 1948 June 14 (Box 8)
  - "Lower Mathematics," typescript carbon, 1948 September 21 (Box 8)
  - "Golden Bowl," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "Mr. Givington," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "Family Reunion," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "Autopsy," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8)
  - "The Rock," typescript carbon, 1949 (Box 8)
  - "Priceless Gift," typescript carbon, 1946 November 19 (Box 8)
  - Sundial of the Seasons, typescript fragment, undated (Box 8)
  - Keep 'Em Rolling, typescript and typescript carbon, circa 1941 (Box 8)
  - "In Memoriam" and "To Keep This Earth Habitable," printed versions in Teacher's College Record, 1963 (Box 8)
  - New York Times editorials, typescript and typescript carbon, 1964-1965 (Box 8)
  - "Sweet Land," typescript carbon, 1945 (Box 8)
  - Colliers Encyclopedia articles, typescript carbon, 1948 (Box 8)
  - "Sweet Land," correspondence, 1945 (Box 8)
  - The Greater Hunger, typescript carbon, circa 1962; 4 (Box 8)
  - The Greater Hunger, printed version, 1962 (Box 8)
  - The Greater Hunger, proofs, circa 1962; 3 (Box 9)
  - The Greater Hunger, typescript, circa 1962; 3 (Box 9)
  - Sundial of the Seasons, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 9)
  - Untitled story, typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 9)
  - This Hill, This Valley, typescript carbon, undated (Box 9)
  - This Hill, This Valley, "Country Scrapbook," typescript and typescript carbon, 1947 (Box 10)
  - This Hill, This Valley, correspondence, 1948-1956 (Box 10)
  - "Data - Berkshire Farm," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 10)
  - This Hill, This Valley, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - High, Wide and Lonesome, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1948-1961 (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1962-1964 (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, correspondence with Bob Pinkerton, 1959-1962 (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on religion, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on gardening, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on customs and clothing, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on Massachusetts Bay Company, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on London, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on voyage, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on Contant, Endecott and Salem in 1620, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes on Winthrop and Boston and Roger Williams, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, notes and quotations, undated (Box 10)
  - The Greater Hunger, bibliography, undated (Box 10)
  - The Dog Who Came to Stay, typescript, 1958 (Box 10)
  - "Calendar Proposal," typescript, undated (Box 10)
  - The Dog Who Came to Stay, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1961 (Box 10)
  - The Dog Who Came to Stay, typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - High, Wide and Lonesome, serialized printed version in Reader's Digest, 1956; 4 (Box 10)
  - The Seventh Winter, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - The Seventh Winter, typescript and typescript carbon, 1959; 2 (Box 11)
  - The Seventh Winter, notes and outline, 1957 (Box 11)
  - The Seventh Winter and The Enduring Pattern, scrapbook of comments and reviews, 1959-1960 (Box 11)
  - When the Legends Die, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 8 (Box 11)
  - Book of Days, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 8 (Box 12)
  - Book of Days, proof, 1976
  - Book of Days, master proof, 1976 (Box 12)
  - When the Legends Die, screenplay, typescript, 1971 July 16 (Box 12)
  - Hill Country Harvest, typescript carbon, 1973-1974; 2 (Box 12)
  - Hill Country Harvest, typescript and typescript carbon, 1960-1965; 3 (Box 13)
  - Hill Country Harvest, typescript carbon, 1959-1965; 2 (Box 13)
  - Hill Country Harvest, typescript carbon and newspaper clippings, 1958-1960 (Box 13)
  - Book of Days, "Daybook: Notes, Anniversaries, Kills, Rejects, etc.," typescript carbon, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - Beyond Your Doorstep, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - The Seventh Winter, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - This Hill, This Valley, typescript, circa 1957; 4 (Box 14)
  - The Greater Hunger, original draft, typescript, circa 1944; 4 (Box 14)
  - This Hill, This Valley, printed in international editions of Reader's Digest, 1957; 2 (Box 14)
  - "The Boy Who Heard the Flowers Bloom," typescript carbon and correspondence, 1954 (Box 14)
  - "Hi, Beautiful!," typescript carbon, undated (Box 14)
  - "October Wanderlust," typescript carbon, 1949 February 22 (Box 14)
  - Book reviews, clippings, 1940s-1960s (Box 14)
  - "Mountain, Desert and Plain," typescript and correspondence, 1955 (Box 14)
  - The Enduring Pattern, typescript, undated (Box 14)
  - Beyond Your Doorstep, correspondence with Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1959-1961 (Box 15)